OBJECTIVE

Management Position in Human Resources

PROFILE

Experienced Human Resources professional with the flexibility to lead efforts related to personnel at all levels of the corporate structure handling a wide variety of functions. Current in local and federal labor laws and best practice to manage issues relating to personnel development and operational streamlining. Sensitive to interpersonal conflicts and quick to address problems before they become critical. Effective leader, manager and qualified decision maker. Bilingual, Spanish and English.

EXPERIENCE

PIETRANTONI MÉNDEZ & ALVAREZ, LLC

San Juan, PR 2006 to 2015

Human Resources Director

Report directly to Managing Partner for large firm specializing in tax, corporate, litigation and labor law with 45 attorneys and 40-member administrative staff. Principal accountabilities include the direct supervision of eight subordinates, strategic design, development and implementation of compensation, salary planning and costing, benefit packages, salary management policies and procedures, employee incentive programs and negotiation health benefit packages. Administer job evaluations and performance review and progressive discipline. Negotiate contract terms with government agencies determining professional fees for legal staff. Secure required insurance and business permits to lower costs, limit risk and firm liability. Manage recruiting and new hire orientation. Administer biweekly payroll for administrative staff and plan periodic/seasonal activities. Purchase office supplies and equipment, decorations and any incentive gifts.

- Created new and modified existing job descriptions providing clarity on responsibilities and performance expectations.
- Represented the firm in administrative hearings before the Department of Labor and Human Resources.
- Reduced tardiness and frequent absences through the creative design and implementation of incentive program.
- Currently developing Employee Handbook including corrective discipline measures for increased organizational communication.

BOTIK San Juan, PR General Manager 2004 to 2006

Instrumental in concept design and development, business structuring and strategic guidance of start-up and continuing development of chic boutique catering to up-scale female consumers. Directed the planning and execution of business strategy and motivational programs for sales personnel with full accountability over service quality standards, operational efficiencies, advertising and competitive merchandising to successfully attain budgeted sales volumes, operational cost parameters and profit targets. Responsible for purchasing, product mix selection, asset protection, deposits and the preparation of cash variances, sales, inventory and personnel reports. Recruited, trained, motivated, supervised and evaluated associates. Planned and posted work schedules and controlled payroll costs.

- Overshot planned revenues 30%.
- Established innovative control and merchandise classification plans that allowed for a highly efficient operation.

HI DEVELOPMENT PUERTO RICO CORP.

San Juan, PR

Human Resources Regional Director, 2000-2004

1994 to 2004

Promoted to direct human resource strategies for the region overseeing safety, recruiting, training, employee/labor relations, disciplinary action, compensation, salary and benefit programs aligned with corporate policies affecting 550-member workforce stationed at three Holiday Inn Hotel and Tropical Casino hotels. Directed and assessed the performance of seven Human Resource professionals, Defined job descriptions, Conducted massive recruiting and training. Controlled payroll costs and investigate/resolve payroll and employment claims. Approved salary increases, negotiated collective bargaining agreements and ensured the proper application of OSHA standards. Monitored and analyzed attendance; Defined and forward motivational and professional development programs. Liaison between company, Puerto Rico and U.S. Department of Labor.

• Initiated improvements in medical insurance program, expanding coverage without additional dollar output.

- Formed part of Executive Committee carrying out corporate decisions.
- Contributed to effective execution of employment law by educating management and supervisory staff on proper procedures in evaluating or dismissing subordinates.
- Orchestrated changes in compensation and salary program, improving salary scales and benefits.
- Designed and implemented incentive programs contributing to a 75% reduction in absenteeism.
- Identified high potential candidates and initiated progression strategies where many candidates grew to middle and senior management level positions.

Personnel Coordinator, 1996-00

Provided support to Human Resource Director in the proactive administration of matters related to exempt and nonexempt personnel. Managed health and life insurance plans, monitored time spent out on sick leave, vacation, maternity and personal functions. Coordinated special events, seminars and workshops. Conducted administrative investigations and prepared case, including all legal documentation for submittal to senior management.

Payroll Clerk, 1994-96

Controlled payroll cycle for 300 Crowne Plaza and Tropical Casino employees. Prepared and paid quarterly income tax retention, social security and drivers insurance.

EDUCATION

San Juan, PR UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO MA Public Administration Major: Personnel Administration

BA Social Science Major: Labor Relations

1990

1994

Cum Laude

IT SKILLS

MS Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook), KRONOS, Hummingbird and Internet Search Engines.